# Yseult Héjja-Brichard

Centre de Recherche Cerveau et Cognition CNRS - Université Paul Sabatier - UMR 5549 Pavillon Baudot - CHU Purpan - BP25202 31052 Toulouse Cedex 03 - France E-mail: yseult.hejja@cnrs.fr - Website: yseulthb.github.io

# RESEARCH INTERESTS

I am currently finishing my PhD studies in cognitive neuroscience and more specifically on depth perception (3D vision) in primate, with a link with natural statistics. For my next research projects, I aim to dive into the fields of sensory ecology and cognitive ecology to further investigate how sensory systems and cognitive functions of different species are shaped by or adapted to the environment in which they evolve.

## **EDUCATION**

# PhD studies Neuroscience, Cognition, and Behaviour

2015-Present

Université Paul Sabatier and CerCo (CNRS), Toulouse, France

Supervisor: Benoit R. Cottereau, within the Eco-3D team.

Title of the thesis: Spatial and temporal integration of binocular disparities in primates.

Synopsis: My PhD project aims to provide a better understanding of how the visual system in primates processes binocular disparities in space and time. I also investigate the relationship between the 3D properties of the environment and neural responses. I mostly conduct functional neuroimaging studies in macaque and collect psychophysics measurements in human and macaque.

## Msc in Neuroscience, Cognition, and Behaviour (2nd year)

2015

Université Paul Sabatier, Toulouse, France

Research project: "Characterisation of the cortical networks involved in 3D orientation processing in primates." at CerCo, Toulouse. Supervised by Benoit R. Cottereau & Jean-Baptiste Durand.

#### Msc in Cognitive and Social Psychology (1st year)

2014

Université de Grenoble-Alpes, Grenoble, France

Research project: "Role of the eyes in face categorisation: Interracial eye change impacts on the other-race effect in a categorisation task." at LPNC, Grenoble. Supervised by Olivier Pascalis. Internship in Neuropsychology at the Hospital of Grenoble, France (January-February 2014)

Bsc in Psychology 2013

Université de Grenoble-Alpes, France & Universität Leipzig, Germany

Research assistant at the Max Planck Institute for Human Cognitive and Brain Sciences, Leipzig, Germany - Department of social neuroscience (April-July 2013). Supervised by Natacha Mendes. *In charge of the coding of chimpanzees' vocalisations collected for an experiment investigating Schadenfreude*.

## SCIENTIFIC PRODUCTION

#### **Publications**

Under review

o Chauhan, T., **Héjja-Brichard, Y.**, & Cottereau, B.R. (*under review*). Modelling binocular disparity processing from statistics in natural scenes.

- o Rima, S., Cottereau, B.R., **Héjja-Brichard**, Y., Trotter, Y. & Durand, J.B. (*under review*). A new visuotopic cluster in macaque posterior parietal cortex revealed by wide-field retinotopy.
- De Castro, V., Smith, A.T., Beer, A.L., Leguen, C., Vayssière, N., Héjja-Brichard, Y., Audurier, P., Cottereau, B.R. Durand, J.B. (*under review*). Connectivity of the cingulate sulcus visual area (CSv) in macaque monkeys.

#### Peer-reviewed journal articles

- Héjja-Brichard, Y., Rima, S., Rapha, E., Durand, J.-B. & Cottereau, B.R. (2020). Stereomotion processing in the non-human primate brain. *Cerebral Cortex*. https://doi.org/10.1093/cercor/bhaa055. [Preprint & OSF project]
- Cottereau, B.R., Smith, A.T., Rima, S., Fize, D., Héjja-Brichard, Y., Renaud, L., ... & Durand, J.-B. (2017). Processing of Egomotion-Consistent Optic Flow in the Rhesus Macaque Cortex. Cerebral Cortex, 1-14. https://doi.org/10.1093/cercor/bhw412

## **Presentations**

#### Invited talks

- Héjja-Brichard, Y. & Mercier M.R. (2018). Data visualisation in cognitive neuroscience: Functional neuroimaging and electrophysiology. Talk given for the Toulouse Data Vizualisation group, Toulouse [Slides]
- **Héjja-Brichard, Y.** (2018). Open Science: Why and How? Talk given at the CerCo's Young Scientist Meeting, Toulouse [Slides]

## Conference talks

Audurier, P., Héjja-Brichard, Y., Kohler, P.J., Norcia, A.M., Durand, J.-B., Cottereau, B.R. (2019).
 Processing of rotational symmetry in the non-human primate brain. Talk given at the annual meeting of the French research group 'GDR Vision', Marseille, France.

#### Conference posters

- Audurier, P., Héjja-Brichard, Y., Kohler, P.J., Norcia, A.M., Durand, J.-B., Cottereau, B.R. (2019, October). Processing of symmetry in the non-human primate brain. Society for Neuroscience, Chicago, USA.
- o De Castro, V., LeGuen, C., **Héjja-Brichard, Y.**, Audurier, P., Cottereau, B.R., Durand, J.-B. (2019, October). Functional and structural connectivity of the cingulate sulcus visual (CSv) area in macaque monkeys. Society for Neuroscience, Chicago, USA.
- Héjja-Brichard, Y., Bruzzone, S.E.P., Rapha, E., Durand, J.-B., Cottereau, B.R. (2019, September).
  Influence of natural statistics on depth perception. Predictive Brain Conference, Marseille, France.
- o **Héjja-Brichard**, Y., Rima, S., Rapha, E., Durand, J.-B., Cottereau, B.R. (2018, November). Stereomotion processing in the non-human primate brain. Society for Neuroscience, San Diego, USA.
- Rima, S., Cottereau, B.R., Héjja-Brichard, Y., Trotter, Y., Durand, J.-B. (2017, November). Wide-field retinotopy reveals a new visuotopic cluster in IPS. Society for Neuroscience, Washington, USA.
- Héjja-Brichard, Y., Rima, S., Durand, J.-B., Cottereau, B.R. (2017, August). Stereomotion processing in the non-human primate brain. European Conference on Visual Perception, Berlin, Germany.
- Héjja-Brichard, Y., Rima, S., Trotter, Y., Banks, M.S., Durand, J.-B., Cottereau, B.R. (2015, October).
  Adaptation to the 3D properties of the environment in non-human primates. GDR Vision annual forum, Grenoble, France.

# RESEARCH SKILLS

#### **Software**

- o Programming: Matlab, Rstudio, C#
- Neuroimaging: SPM12, caret5 (surface-based software for monkey data), PRoNTo (Pattern recognition toolbox)
- o Stimulus presentation: EventIDE (advanced), PsychToolbox (basics), Eprime
- o Writing: LaTeX, RMarkdown, Office
- o Graphics editor: Adobe Illustrator, Photoshop
- o Data and article sharing: Github, Open Science Framework, bioRxiv

# Data analysis

- o fMRI data analyses: whole-brain, region-of-interest-based, and retinotopic analyses; MVPA
- Psychophysical data modelling
- Eye-tracking analysis (basics)

# TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Temporary teaching assistant (2019-2020) for Bsc Psychology students (1<sup>st</sup> year) - 48 hrs Department of Psychology, Université Toulouse Jean Jaurès, Toulouse, France. Tutorial classes ('TD').

Graduate teaching assistant (2015-2018) for Bsc Biology students (2<sup>nd</sup> and 3<sup>rd</sup> years) - 193 hrs Department of neuroscience and behavioural science, Université Paul Sabatier, Toulouse, France. Practical works ('TP') and tutorial classes ('TD').

#### 2019-2020

T., t.,	1 - D11-	: -1 (DC)	(C 1st)	TTD: 401-
Introduction	to Psychoph	VS10109V (P5Y	C. 1st vear)	TD: 48h

#### 2017-2018

Nervous and cerebral functions (BCP, 3 <sup>rd</sup> year)	TD: 4h & TP: 33h

Behavioural ecology (BOPE, 3<sup>rd</sup> year) TP: 27h

#### 2016-2017

Neurophysiology	(BCP 2 <sup>nd</sup> year)	TD: 4h

Nervous and cerebral functions (BCP, 3<sup>rd</sup> year) TD: 4h & TP: 36h

Behavioural ecology (BOPE, 3<sup>rd</sup> year) TP: 21h

#### 2015-2016

Neuroscience (BCP, 2<sup>nd</sup> year) TP: 24h

Nervous and cerebral functions (BCP, 3<sup>rd</sup> year) TD: 6h & TP: 28h

Behavioural ecology (BOPE, 3<sup>rd</sup> year) TP: 6h

PSYC: Psychology; BCP: Cell Biology and Physiology; BOPE: Organisms, Populations, and Ecosystems Biology

# Student supervision

- o 2019: Master's student in Neuroscience, Università degli studi di Trieste, Italy Psychophysics
- o 2018: Master's student in Neuroscience, University of Bordeaux, France fMRI analyses

## **Volunteering French teacher**

 2015-2016: Teaching French as a foreign language (FLE) to adults for the NGO "Croissant Fertile", Toulouse, France

# **EXTRACURRICULAR ACTIVITIES**

#### Lab Community Involvement

- Organisation of the first edition of the Lab Student Day (2019)
- o Co-creation of a Welcome Kit for new students and postdocs (2019)
- Student representative at the Lab Council (2017-2018)
- Organisation of the Lab Winter School (2017, 2018)
- o Co-organisation of the Annual 'CerCo Day' (2016)
- Ambassador for the Center for Open Science: COS (2018-present)
- Development of a collective with other young researchers to promote open and slow science

# Personal Implication in Science Popularisation

- o Public presentation on visual illusions (March 2019) for the Brain Awareness Week at Quai des Savoirs, a cultural centre in Toulouse: "Les illusions visuelles, une illusion du cerveau?"
- o Public presentation on the study of 3D vision in animals (February 2017) "En tête à tête avec un jeune chercheur", Museum de Toulouse: "La vision 3D : mieux qu'au cinéma!"
- o Article written for the Museum of Natural sciences of Toulouse (March 2017, in French) about the evolution of 3D vision in animals. Yseult Héjja-Brichard & Benoit R. Cottereau "Evolution et vision : le vivant a de la profondeur!"
- Communications manager and member of InCOGnu an organisation of students and young researchers in cognitive science in the Toulouse area.
   Organisation of monthly conferences, workshops for the general public (both adults and children) and participation in various events of science popularisation (Pint of Science, EuroScience Open Forum, Brain Awareness Week, National Forum of Cognitive Science).

# Complementary skills and training

- Languages French (native), English (full proficiency), German (good command in speaking, level B2), Spanish (basic communication skills, level B1).
- Methodological improvement Workshops in statistical analyses and in ethics
- Certification Experimental research design in non-human primates, June 2016 (CNRS Marseille)